McGregor Plan records, Inclusive: 1936-1942, undated, Bulk: 1937-1940
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
McGregor Plan records
Inclusive: 1936-1942, undated, Bulk: 1937-1940
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
171
The Texas Collection, 1923 -
1 document box.
The McGregor Plan records consist of materials documenting the Baylor University Texas Collection's participation in the McGregor Plan. The McGregor Plan assisted smaller libraries who lacked resources and access to book dealers in purchasing rare Americana to add to their holdings.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
The Texas Collection, a Baylor University special library, participated in the McGregor Plan from 1936-1942. As one of a very select group of participants in the McGregor Plan, the story of Baylor's involvement in the plan is also the story of the McGregor Plan itself.
Tracy W. McGregor was a multi-millionaire who collected rare Americana as a hobby. In 1933, he desired to unite his humanitarian efforts with his love of books and the result was the McGregor Plan, officially known as the "McGregor Plan for the Encouragement of Book Collecting by American College Libraries." Under the supervision of the American Historical Association’s Committee on Americana for College Libraries, McGregor selected and bought books identified as important and sold them at cost to libraries who needed help in expanding their rare book holdings. Universities and colleges applied to be accepted by the McGregor Plan and had to meet several stipulations. They could not be near a university with a significant holding of Americana or in a large metropolitan area. The university or college also had to be willing to match the McGregor Fund’s (the group responsible for the financial side of McGregor’s estate) annual donation of $500 through outside donations and alumni support, combining for a total of $1,000 to be spent annually on rare Americana. The books acquired through the McGregor Plan had to be marked as rare books and could not be defaced in any way. Baylor University’s Texas Collection was one of fifteen libraries accepted to the program by 1936. McGregor died unexpectedly on 1936 May 6, but his plan continued under the leadership of Randolph G. Adams. The headquarters of the plan transferred from Washington D.C. to the Clements Library at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor. The plan flourished until the economic strain of World War II resulted in a vote for the plan’s suspension in November 1942. After the end of the war, the plan did not receive enough support from the McGregor Fund’s trustees to restart and the remainder of Mr. McGregor’s collection was liquidated among the participating libraries.
Scope and Content
The collection begins in 1936 and ends in 1942. Most of the collection includes the correspondence between two library directors Dr. E. W. McDiarmid and Dr. William Stanley Hoole, The Texas Collection librarian Professor Guy B. Harrison and the chairman of the committee which administrated and oversaw the McGregor Plan, Randolph G. Adams, or his secretary and assistant director, Kathryn L. Slagle.
The majority of the documents include book catalogues from the McGregor Plan, lists of the books the Texas Collection requested to be purchased and received through the McGregor Plan, and financial records pertaining to the purchase of these books. The early correspondence features Baylor’s initial inquiry into the program and their eventual selection as one of the schools benefiting from the McGregor Plan. The collection also includes an informational pamphlet describing the McGregor Plan and a list of all the Texas Collection’s holdings purchased as part of the plan.
Arrangement
Prior to current processing, the collection materials were housed in one folder in reverse chronological order. The collection is now spread across multiple folders and is arranged in chronological order, starting with the earliest date and moving to the latest.
The collection is arranged in two series, I. Correspondence and II. Books Found in the Texas Collection.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 171. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
American Historical Association, Committee on Americana for College Libraries. The McGregor Plan for the Encouragement of Book Collecting by American College Libraries. Ann Arbor: American Historical Association, Committee on Americana for College Libraries, 1937.
Interview of Guy B. Harrison, Jr. by Thomas L. Charlton and Kent Keeth. 1974 June 28. Transcript, Baylor University Institute for Oral History, Waco, Texas.
Mason, Philip P. Tracy W. McGregor: Humanitarian, Philanthropist, and Detroit Civic Leader. Detroit: Wayne State University Press, 2008. p. 192-198.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951 -- Correspondence.; Harrison, Guy Bryan -- Correspondence.; Hoole, William Stanley, 1903-1990 -- Correspondence.; McDiarmid, E. W. (Errett Weir), 1909-2000 -- Correspondence.; McGregor, Tracy W. (Tracy William), 1869-1936.; Slagle, Kathryn L. -- Correspondence.
Subjects (Organizations)
American Historical Association. Committee on Americana for College Libraries.; McGregor Fund -- Records and correspondence.
Subjects
Academic libraries -- Collection development.; Americana -- Catalogs.; Americana.; Rare book libraries -- Texas -- Waco.
- Correspondence, 1936-1942, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The series contains letters exchanged between the representatives of the McGregor Plan and librarians at the Texas Collection. The series is in good condition.
  - Informational Booklet, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters (1 of 8), 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters (2 of 8), 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters (3 of 8), 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters (4 of 8), 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters (5 of 8), 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters (6 of 8), 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters (7 of 8), 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters (8 of 8), 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Books Found in the Texas Collection, undated; 2
  This series contains a list of all the books in the Texas Collection purchased through the McGregor Plan. The series is in good condition.
  - Book Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)